However we are starting. Okay. All right, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*.
So,
today's דף daf *Daf* is צדי א׳ *Tzadi Alef*, 91, and we
pick up where we're a little bit behind. We pick up in
the middle of צדי עמוד ב׳ *Tzadi Amud Bet*, 90b, and we
pick up with ואחת בחייו *v'achas b'chayav*. It is five
lines down in the wide line. And we're dealing with the issue
of this complicated case. So our new participants came at a perfect
time, which basically is Reuven is married to two wives. First he
marries Rachel, who has a כתובה ktuva, *Ketubah* of $20,000.
Rachel dies, so he keeps that money that otherwise he would have
paid out to Rachel. But the principle of כתובת בנין דכרין ktuvat
bnin dichrin, *Ketubat Benin Dichrin* means that when he dies, Rachel's kids
are going to get that prior to any other kids he's got.
And then he also married Leah, and Leah survives his death. So
now Leah's kids are coming to collect their mother's כתובה ktuva, *Ketubah*.
They're basically acting as creditors, whereas Rachel's kids want to get their
$20,000 that their father inherited from their mom as an inheritance, okay?
So they're coming as heirs and they want their chunk before the
whole estate gets divided. And Leah or Leah's kids are coming as
creditors and they want Leah's כתובה ktuva *Ketubah* paid up. So that's
called אחת בחייו ואחת במותו *Achas B'chayav v'achas B'moso*. Okay,
these guys, their mother died when Reuven was alive. Here the mother
basically died after Reuven had died. These are coming from the principle
of כתובת בנין דכרין ktuvat bnin dichrin *Ketubat Benin Dichrin* as heirs,
and Leah's kids are coming as again as creditors or as children
of the creditor, and the basic ruling of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*
is that Leah's kids collect their כתובה ktuva *Ketubah*, and then Rachel's
kids get their portion as their inheritance, and then the rest is
divided equally. Okay, that was... Yes, debt trumps inheritance. Debt, well, yeah,
that's always the case. Somebody dies, the creditors come and they collect
from the estate.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: but the
question, if you remember that we raised yesterday, was whether in this
case Rachel's kids are entitled to any special chunk because Leah's kids
could say, why do you get a larger portion of the estate?
When both Leah and Rachel had died before Reuven, so Leah's kids
get the portion that their mother had brought in, that was their
mother's כתובה ktuva *Ketubah* as their first takeaway from the estate, and
Leah's kids get what their mother's כתובה ketubah *Ketubah* as their first
takeaway from the estate, and the rest is divided equally. They both
are entitled to the special ruling of כתובת בנין דכרין kesuvas benin
dichrin *Ketubat Benin Dichrin*, right? Of inheriting their mother's כתובה ketubah. *Ketubah*.
But in this case, Leah's kids aren't inheriting their mother's כתובה kesuvah.
*Ketubah*.
Reuven died before Leah. They're just collecting their mother's debt. So maybe
they should be able to say to Rachel's kids, it's not fair
that you get a special right as an inheritance that we're not
getting. Was it written in as a clause?
It was just otherwise applied. Yes. That, well, sometimes it was, sometimes
it wasn't.
Like we don't write it in, it was just one of those
תנאי בית דין Beit Din *T'nai Beit Din*.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes it that way
even when they don't write it. Yeah, but it is true the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* definitely did have it at times that it was
written in. ולעולם אם *U'le'olam im* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* like
this: so the אחת בחייו ואחת במותו *v'achas b'chayav v'achas b'moso*. So
now says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* five lines down in the wide
lines on צדי עמוד ב׳ *Tzadi Amud Bet*. So this issue of
one while he's alive and one
and Leah died after he died. תנאי *Tannai*, this is the debate
of the תנאים Tannaim *Tannaim* whether the principle of כתובת בנין דכרין
ketubat benin dichrin *Ketubat Benin Dichrin* still applies. דתניא detanya *De-tanya*, we
learned in a ברייתא Braisa. *Baraita*: מתו *Mesu*. So here it's explicit.
The wives died. אחת בחייו *Achas b'chayav*, one died while he was
alive, Rachel died while he was alive, ואחת במותו *v'achas b'moso*, and
then Leah died after he had died. So exactly this case. בן
ננס Benanas? אומר *Ben Nanas omer*, Ben Nanas says, יכולין בני ראשונה
לומר לבני שנייה *yecholin bnei rishona lomar livnei shniya*, so the children
of the first one could say to the children of the second
one, meaning Rachel's kids could say to Leah's kids, בני בעלת חוב
אתם *bnei ba'alat chov attem*, you are heirs of your mother who
had a debt against the estate because our father died while your
mother was still alive, so your mother had a debt of the
כתובה kesuvah. *Ketubah* against the estate. טלו כתובת אמכם וצאו *t'lu ketubat
immachem utze'u*, go take your mother's כתובה kesuvah, *Ketubah* and leave. Okay.
רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva omer, *Rabbi Akiva omer*, now Rabbi Akiva
says, כבר קפצה נחלה kvar kaftzah nachalah, לפני בני ראשונה ונפלה לפני
בני שנייה *kvar kaftza nachala lifnei bnei rishona v'nafla lifnei bnei shniya*,
the special inheritance that the children of the first one would get,
that Rachel's kids would get, has jumped away from them and has
fallen in front of the Leah's kids. Now, that's very colorful language,
but it... it's not exactly clear what he's saying, but it's pretty
clear what he's basically saying is that they had this twenty thousand
dollars they were going to take away from the estate and somehow
they lost their grip on it. Okay, they're not going to get
it. It's now all going to be evenly divided. So basically בן
ננס Benanas says, was it בן ננס? Benanas Yes.
Okay, בן
ננס Benanas says, לאה's Leah kids come and they take their mother's
debt and then רחל's Rachel kids are still entitled to their special
portion of the estate. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I'm sorry
they don't they lose their special portion it all gets divided equally.
So let's take a look. So גמרא Gemara says like this, wow,
lot of commotion going on today. So גמרא Gemara says like this,
מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי,
Mai
lav
beha kamiflegi,
don't we say this is what they're debating about? דמר סבר אחת
בחיי ואחת במות יש להן כתובת בנין דכרין, Demar savar achat bechayai
veachat bemoto yesh lahen ktuvat bnin dichrin, one בן ננס Benanas says
they're still entitled so as long as to their extra to their
special section of the estate even you know even though only רחל's
Rachel kids are entitled to that and not לאה's Leah kids. ומר
סבר אחת בחיי ואחת במות אין להן כתובת בנין דכרין Umar savar
achat bechayai veachat bemoto ein lahen ktuvat bnin dichrin
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, they're not since they're not
both getting it as a special inheritance, then בני רחל's Bnei Rachel
kids lose out. So that sounds like what they're debating. So the
גמרא Gemara says ומר סבר אין להן כתובת בנין
דכרין. Umar savar ein lahen ktuvat bnin dichrin. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
so רבא Rava says, אשכחתינהו לרבנן דבי רב, Ashkachtinhu lerabbanan devei Rav,
I found the Rabbis like you know of the house of רב
Rav of the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב Rav דיתבי וקאמרי deyatvi veka'amri
and they were analyzing this debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
בן ננס Ben Nannas which certainly sounds like this is what they're
debating. And they said the following not necessarily, we could say דכולי
עלמא אחת בחיי ואחת במות יש להן כתובת בנין דכרין. dekulei alma
achat bechayai veachat bemoto yesh lahen ktuvat bnin dichrin. Everybody agrees that
basically in this type of a case רחל's Rachel kids are entitled
to their special you know to get their special section of the
estate before it gets divided equally. והכא בכתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה והוא
הדין לבעל חוב קמיפלגי Vehacha bektuva na'asit motar lachaverta vehu hadin leva'al
chov kamiflegi
they're debating the issue we said because you'll remember that even when
there is כתובת בנין דכרין, ketubat benin dichrin. that's only when there's
leftover money to apply the normal rules of inheritance to. You can't
have כתובת בנין דכרין kesubas bnin dichrin being the entire amount of
the estate. There has to be leftover money for there to be
a normal inheritance. So in this case לאה's Leah kids come, they
take out their ten thousand dollar estate, their ten thousand dollar debt.
All you're left with is the twenty thousand dollars. There's nothing more.
So if רחל's Rachel kids come and they take their mother's special
inheritance, twenty thousand dollars, nobody gets a normal inheritance. Nothing gets divided
equally. Okay, so that's what רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva saying. רבי עקיבא's
Rabbi Akiva saying basically, oh, you had it in your grasp, but
it jumped away from you. It jumped away from you because there's
nothing left over to divide equally. Now we're going to have to
divide that you lost your special rights to that. Whereas בן ננס
is going to say no, no, no, no, no, there was a
normal inheritance, right? What was that normal inheritance? The money that לאה's
Leah kids as creditors came to collect, that was being paid out
by the estate. So that was what was inherited equally by all
of the heirs. They paid out the creditors. All they paid the
creditors then there's twenty thousand dollars left but רחל's Rachel kids walked
away with. Okay, so that is okay because it is like there
is stuff that the normal rules of inheritance apply to. That was
the money the heirs paid out to לאה. Leah.
לאה's Leah kids, רחל's Rochel kids throw in a dollar?
No, and we're going to see that later.
Okay, but why does it have to be a normal inheritance?
That's just what the רבנן Rabbanan said, they're not going to make
this rule of giving רחל's Rachel kids a special status of an
heirs to override the תורה's Torah normal division of inheritance. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this, so והכא בכתובה נעשית מותר
לחברתה, Vehacha bektuva na'asit motar lachaverta, when one כתובה, kesuvah לאה's Leah
כתובה, ketubah be considered that the money paid out you know basically
is considered leftover funds as it were to allow רחל's Rachel כתובה
ketubah, to be effective. Meaning the fact that they paid out לאה's
Leah כתובה ketubah means
that there was a normal part of the inheritance that existed so
that now that's like the מותר דינא motar dina or the extra
money so that רחל's Rachel כתובה ketubah can so that רחל's Rachel
kids can still collect. והוא הדין לבעל חוב, Vehuhu hadin leva'al chov,
and it would have been the same question if it was just
some stranger coming in and collecting and the estate paid out. Would
money that the estate paid out be considered, oh, so there was
a normal inheritance that took place and now רחל's Rachel kids are
entitled to their special inheritance?
We don't worry about
that right, we don't worry about it? Well, yes, well we'll worry
about that yes, but that is correct. Okay, so that's how they
explain the debate. ומר סבר אין כתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה והוא הדין
לבעל חוב. Umar savar ein ktuva na'asit motar lachaverta vehuhu hadin leva'al
chov. Okay, that's reasonable. So they're not debating in principle whether רחל's
Rachel kids have a right to it, but whether this is the
case that they're entitled to it, was there any leftover money in
the estate? ואמינא להו אנא, Va'amina lehu ana,
and now says רבא, Rava, I said back to them,
דמר סבר אין כתובה נעשית
מותר.
Demar savar ein ktuva
na'asit motar.
I read that. Okay. And I said back to them, בבעל חוב
כולי עלמא לא פליגי דהוי מותר. Be'ba'al chov kulei alma lo peligi
dehavi motar. No, no, no, in a simple case where some stranger
came where you know I don't know, ברק, Barak, and now I'm
getting back to when we learned יבמות. Yevamot. ברק Barak was always
the stranger, he wasn't part of the same family. Okay so when
ברק Barak came and he collected his ten thousand dollar debt, then
everybody would agree, okay, you paid off some stranger from the estate.
That was the normal inheritance right and that everybody paid equally and
every all of the heirs equally owed that debt and paid it
from their estate, and then so there's leftover there was a part
that was a normal inheritance and now רחל's Rachel kids are entitled
to get their special their special inheritance. So if it was a
stranger everybody would agree that רחל's Rachel kids would be entitled. כי
פליגי, ki pleigi, what do they debate? The כתובה ketubah. in this
case where it's not ברק Barak kids that are coming לאה's Leah
kids are coming to collect their mother's debt. So in that case
basically לאה's Leah kids could say, you know, you got we didn't
get a normal part of the inheritance. So when רחל's Rachel kids
says oh yes you did get a normal part of the inheritance
we all got it and then we used it to pay you
off. So when you're paying yourself back for your own debt it's
not so much like, you know, it's it's different right, it doesn't
feel like basically that was a normal part of the process of
inheritance that took place. No, no, no, we're first getting paid and
then we'll worry about inheritance. You don't see it as a we
all inherited and now we're paying ourselves. Okay so that's the issue.
So basically you get back to this question in this special case
there's a couple of questions whether רחל's Rachel kids gets to take
out their mother's כתובה. ketubah Number one, because לאה's Leah kids aren't
in that status, לאה's Leah kids aren't in the status of special
heirs, לאה's Leah kids are coming as creditors, and number two, thank
you, even when we do say רחל's Rachel kids in principle are
entitled that's only when there's leftover money in the estate afterwards. Is
it considered leftover money of the estate if there's no leftover money
because money was used to pay out a creditor? And that would
be a question of a general creditor, and it's maybe even a
harder answer to say yes to when the creditor is actually לאה's
Leah kids themselves. Yes.
So this is really just a matter of technicality in some ways
because if I were just let's say bequeathed, is it in a
מתנה? matanah? Yeah, and I give a מתנה matanah of ten thousand
and I give מתנה matanah of twenty thousand they don't need that
extra דינר. dinar.
Right, correct, correct, correct. But we're not going to give them a
position of special heirs to override an actual inheritance. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara, says like this.
Okay, that was very quickly lived. We're going to look forward to
seeing you tomorrow.
All right. All right well keep on trying. All right so the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
מתקיף לה רב יוסף, maskif lah Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav
Yosef asks on what רב Rav said. אי הכי ei hachi רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר,
if that's true, then why do we have a phrase that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva saying כבר קפצה נחלה, that the inheritance jumped away
from רחל's Rachel kids, they lost their grip on their special inheritance?
Okay, since what he's really not saying is that not in principle
they didn't have a right to it but it was just a
circumstantially because there was no leftover money. So he should have been
more specific he should have said אם יש מותר דינר מיבעי ליה.
im yesh mosar dinar mibaei lei. He should have said רחל's Rachel
kids can get it if there's leftover money. So since he didn't
say that, it sounded like in principle רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would
say that in this type of case רחל's Rachel kids are never
going to get it. אלא אמר רב יוסף, ela amar Rav Yosef,
so rather רב יוסף Rav Yosef says באחת בחייו ובאחת במותו קמיפלגי,
be'achas bechayav ube'achas bemoso kamiflagi, they really do debate the fundamental principle,
okay. So this case he says for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is
saying that רחל's Rachel kids don't get it, it's not because it
was a special circumstance that there was not any leftover money in
the estate, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in principle is saying the only
time רחל's Rachel kids are special have an opportunity to be special
heirs is when לאה's Leah kids are special heirs as well, but
if לאה's Leah kids are not special heirs, they're coming as creditors,
then רחל's Rachel kids do not have their status. Okay, so that
remains the debate. והני תנאי כי הני תנאי vahani tannai kihani tannai
and these תנאים Tannaim. of רבי עקיבא and בן ננס who debate
this issue about do we say כתובת בנין דכרין kesubas bnin dichrin
when it only applies to one set of kids is like the
following תנאים. דתניא as it's taught in a ברייתא. braisa נשא את
הראשונה ומתה, nasa es harishonah umesah,
so a man married the first wife רחל Rachel and then רחל
Rachel died. Okay, so again it's the same case. ונשא את השנייה,
venasa es hashniyah, then he married the second wife לאה, Leah, ומת
הוא, umes hu, and he died. באים בניה של זו ba'im bneia
shel zo the kids of the first of this wife of this
one, not clear which one but there's a question here of what
the גירסא girsa was, anyway we're talking about לאה's Leah kids. לאה's
Leah kids come לאחר מיתה le'achar misah after after their mother has
now died because remember first ראובן Reuven died and then לאה Leah
was still survived him. So now their mother has died and now
they come ונוטלין כתובת אמן venotlin kesuvas iman and they collect their
mother's כתובה. ketubah Okay, that's not a big חידוש, chiddush, of course
they collect their mother's כתובה. ketubah רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer,
now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says אם יש מותר דינר, im yesh
mosar dinar,
if there's that extra דינר dinar after the money's been paid out,
then אלו נוטלין כתובת אמן ואלו נוטלין כתובת אמן. elu notlin kesuvas
iman ve'elu notlin kesuvas iman. Then רחל's Rachel kids not only can
לאה's Leah kids get their mother's כתובה, ketubah, רחל's Rachel kids can
get their mother's כתובה ketubah as well as special heirs. ואם לאו
ve'im lav but if there's not an extra דינר dinar right leftover
in the estate then חולקין בשווה cholkin beshaveh they divide equally. So
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon basically is reiterating this principle that we know
that there has to be a leftover דינר dinar in order for
the רחל's Rachel kids to have the special. position of special heirs.
Okay, fine. But in principle, רחל's Rachel kids are entitled to take
their mother's כתובה ketubah out of the estate, even though לאה's Leah
kids are not coming as special heirs, they're coming as creditors. What
is the first position? The first position doesn't mention רחל's Rachel kids.
The first position just says לאה's Leah kids come and collect. Sounds
like רחל's Rachel kids get nothing, I mean they're equal, they don't
get any special כתובה, ketubah right? So it sounds like they're debating
whether in this case that these here are that these are heirs
and these are creditors, whether רחל's Rachel kids are entitled to their
status as special heirs. Okay, the second position, I'm forgetting who said
it, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said yes, as long as there's an
extra דינר, dinar, but the first position did not indicate that רחל's
Rachel kids get any special takeaway. Let me just read one minute.
Okay, so מאי לאו, mai lav, so the גמרא Gemara says, בהא
קמיפלגי, beha kamiflegi, it sounds like they debate. דמר סבר אחד בחייו
ואחד במותו יש להם כתובת בנין דכרין, demar savar echad bechayav ve'echad
bemoto yesh lahem ketubat benin dichrin, one, and now it's actually saying
it in the opposite order, but okay. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds
that the רחל's Rachel kids are entitled to כתובת בנין דכרין kesubas
bnin dichrin as long as there's that extra דינר. dinar. ומר סבר
אחד בחייו ואחד במותו אין להם כתובת בנין דכרין. umar savar echad
bechayav ve'echad bemoto ein lahem ketubat benin dichrin.
No, רחל's Rachel kids are not entitled to their special status and
לאה's Leah kids get their כתובה ketuvah and mother's כתובה ketuvah and
then the rest is divided equally. So okay. So you had a
question, Jonathan?
Just to make sure that when we're translating special heirs we're referring
to בנין דכרין. benin dichrin.
Yes, I was using that because it occurred to me that that's
a nice sort of way, yes, that's the quaint phrase I just
coined for כתובת בנין דכרין.
ketuvas benin dikhrin Can you just re-clarify, like what's the difference between
what בנין דכרין benin dichrin adds and the fact that the sons
normally inherit?
Because if there are sons from a different mother, then if you
just apply the normal rules of inheritance, everybody would get an equal
portion. But if you specify, but רחל's Rachel kids before the whole
estate is divided equally, they first take out the money that was
in their mother's כתובה. ketuvah Okay, so if the mother brought in
twenty thousand dollars in her כתובה ketuvah or however much she brought
in, but the face value of the כתובה ketuvah was twenty thousand
dollars, was never paid out because their mother died before their father
died, so the father never paid that כתובה ketuvah out to their
mother. So they now take twenty thousand dollars out of the estate
when their father dies before it now gets divided equally among all
the heirs.
And this is a vehicle really for protecting the inheritance of the
children of one mother as opposed to the children of another.
Yes, and actually what the גמרא Gemara correct, and actually as the
way the גמרא Gemara says it, is that it gets back to
the whole social realities about the כתובה, ketuvah is that a father
who is not going to give a big dowry to his daughter
if he thinks maybe my daughter will have one kid and this
guy will marry another woman and have ten kids and this huge
dowry I'm giving my daughter is not going to stay within my
grandchildren, within my family. So now I know that however much money
I give to my daughter when she's getting married through the dowry
will stay with her kids. Okay, so now the גמרא, Gemara yeah.
This thing about the extra דינר dinar is after what?
After the,
that if after רחל's Rachel kids were to take their special inheritance
there would be a leftover דינר, dinar, then that allows them to
take their special inheritance. But if by taking their special inheritance no
money is left over in the estate, then they're not, then they
lose that right.
And they're taking it after the second children are getting their?
Yeah, exactly. And that becomes a question: does the money used to
pay the second children count as that extra money or not? That's
the other question. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay,
it's all the same question being asked in different ways. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
לא, lo, not necessarily, that's not necessarily the debate of רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. דכולי עלמא אחד בחייו
ואחד במותו יש להם כתובת בנין דכרין. dechulei alma echad bechayav ve'echad
bemoto yesh lahem ketubat benin dichrin. We could say that everybody agrees
in principle רחל's Rachel kids are entitled to it. So why does
it sound like the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma ignored רחל's Rachel kids?
והכא, vehacha, top of צא tzadi aleph עמוד א. amud aleph. והכא
בדינר מקרקעי קמיפלגי. vehacha bedinar mekarkai kamiflegi. So now Michael, you see
Michael, you always anticipate everything the גמרא's Gemara going to say. The
question is, what if when we say we have to have leftover
money, leftover money in landed property or any leftover money? Okay, so
he's saying that it's only if there's leftover money in landed property,
that's considered because that was considered like obviously like the real, you
know, sort of symbol of the inheritance, even though of course nowadays
obviously you could have billions of dollars in some, you know, in
some stock or whatever, but nevertheless that was considered to be the
real thing. So that would be what would be symbolic of actually
having a real biblical inheritance was that there was some landed estate
that they divided equally. מר סבר מקרקעי אין מטלטלין לא. mar savar
mekarkai in metaltelin lo.
So one holds that only if it's landed estate, so therefore the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was saying רחל's Rachel kids don't get it
because we'd be talking about a case where there was no landed
estate leftover, that extra דינר dinar leftover. ומר סבר umar savar and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said, אפילו מטלטלין, afilu metaltelin, even if there's
any extra דינר dinar leftover that entitles רחל's Rachel kids, even from
cattle.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי מצית אמרת הכי, umi matzit amart
hachi, how could you say that, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
that any extra דינר dinar even from cattle allows this to operate?
והתנן, vehatnan, we're going to teach in the משנה, Mishnah the משנה
Mishna at the bottom of this page actually, we're about to see.
ר' שמעון אומר Reb Shimon omer ר' שמעון Reb Shimon says אפילו
יש שם נכסים שאינם אחריות afilu yeish sham nechasim she'einam achrayus even
if
there is property that is unencumbered meaning not not unencumbered that is
not that would never be encumbered meaning if there's cattle even if
there's leftover cattle אינו כלום eino klum it doesn't count to allow
you know רחל's Rochel kids to take their their to take their
כתובת בנין דכרין ketuvas benin dikhrin okay that doesn't count as money
left over in the estate to allow the special status of כתובת
בנין דכרין ketuvas benin dikhrin. to apply עד שיהא שם נכסים שיש
להן אחריות יתירי על שתי כתובות בית דין ad she'hei sham nechasim
sheyeish lahen achrayus yeisirei al shtei kesubos beis din if you want
the the special you know rule of כתובת בנין דכרין Ketubat Benin
Dikhrin. to apply then we say there has to be some money
left over after everybody takes away their special inheritance okay that only
will be if what's left over is actually a piece of land
if there's a piece of land worth a דינר denar left over
then we'll say it but otherwise we won't say
it exact same logic
right exactly or I don't know why can't people say like okay
I will take my inheritance from the cattle so that the land
will be left over right maybe they can't say that okay anyway
אלא ela so it can't be that ר' שמעון Reb Shimon is
saying oh no they're entitled because it doesn't have to be from
land because ר' שמעון Reb Shimon is the one that actually says
it has to be from land the leftover in order for them
to be entitled אלא הכא בדינא משעבדי קמיפלגי ela hacha bdina meshubadei
kamiflugei okay here the question is let's say there is a leftover
amount but that leftover amount is actually somebody else has a lien
on it okay so here's the actual scenario you get it right
so you got these two kids they're coming even a simpler case
than this each set of kids is coming with their own special
inheritance to take out before anything gets divided obviously the ones that
get a bigger chunk are the ones that want to ensure the
special rules apply okay and they're coming and there has to be
after everybody takes out their special inheritance something left over there will
be something left over but what's left over and it will even
be land only trouble is that there are some creditors that's got
their eyes on that they've got some liens on that so can
they so can basically they say oh that's not really like there's
anything left over because we're all going to lose it sooner or
later because the creditors are going to come and take it right
so it's not really left over which somewhat relates to the idea
of maybe actually money paid to creditors counts as left over
what yeah
could the kids pay off the lien so that they have the
land ah
yeah that would be like the smart thing to do is first
pay off the lien before it gets around I mean then the
other questions like what time do you at what moment do you
assess what the status is which what we're going to get to
it but yeah that would be the smart thing to do what
we learned earlier is that even if the land was already paid
to creditors it might count as if it was left over because
then the estate paid the creditor that's like the estate inherit everybody
inherited it here we're going even further not only if it's paid
does it doesn't count maybe even the fact that it might get
paid right that it has a lien on it might make it
considered not left over property to allow these special rules to apply
okay מר
סבר mar savar אלא הכא בדינא משעבדי קמיפלגי ela hacha bdina meshubadei
kamiflugei מר סבר mar savar מבני חורין אין ממשעבדי לא mibnei chorin
in mimeshubadei lo the תנא קמא tana kama who basically says that
רחל's Rochel kids get nothing would be a case where the leftover
amount would only be would have been encumbered would have had liens
on it and the תנא קמא tana kama said no it's only
going to count as a leftover amount if it's unencumbered if it
has no liens on it not if it has liens on it
and therefore רחל's Rochel kids get nothing ומר סבר u'mar savar ר'
שמעון Reb Shimon says as long as there's a דינר denar left
over רחל's Rochel kids get he holds אפילו ממשעבדי afilu mimeshubadei that
no even if that extra דינר denar has a lien on it
as long as there's some extra דינר denar of land even if
it has a lien on it רחל's Rochel kids are entitled so
okay so that's a reasonable real although again it's reading a lot
into the into the ברייתא braisa right exactly but it's reading a
lot into the ברייתא braisa because the ברייתא Braisa didn't say it
was a special case that there was something anyway but okay that's
what it wants to say is the debate אי הכי ei hachi
says גמרא Gemara if that's true so ר' שמעון Reb Shimon is
coming to be to be like lenient as it were for רחל's
Rochel kids and say as long as there's an extra דינר denar
even if it has liens on it רחל's Rochel kids are entitled
if that's true ר' שמעון אומר Reb Shimon omer אם יש שם
מותר דינר im yeish sham mosear denar if there's an extra דינר
denar then רחל's Rochel kids will get it that's not phrased right
that sounds like that he's making a demand you know I'm not
going to let you guys get it unless you've got an extra
דינר denar what you're telling me is ר' שמעון Reb Shimon is
actually coming and saying that he's lowering the demand so what it
should have said was what it should have said was אם יש
שם מותר דינר im yeish sham mosear denar it he should have
said כיון שיש שם מותר דינר מיבעי ליה keivan sheyeish sham mosear
denar mibai lei he should have said look you תנא קמא tana
kama say the kids don't get it because it's encumbered I say
as long as since there's since there's a דינר denar there they're
entitled even if it has the liens on it okay so the
language where ר' שמעון Reb Shimon says אם יש שם im yeish
sham sounds like ר' שמעון Reb Shimon is creating greater demands not
lesser demands okay so that does not work with the way we're
trying to frame it so again it sounds like the תנא קמא
tana kama saying that רחל's Rochel kids get nothing ר' שמעון Reb
Shimon is saying רחל's Rochel kids are entitled if there is a
דינר denar so one way to explain that is this fundamental question
of when they're coming from different
positions. But if that's true we have to structure it so that
it works with the language of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon where it
sounds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is actually making being more strict,
not being more lenient, okay? So we had a reasonable read but
it just didn't work with the close reading of the language. So
let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes from here. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
אלא בפחות מדינר קמיפלגי. ela be-pachos mi-dinar kamifligi.
Fine. The debate is, until now we've been assuming that there has
to be an extra דינר dinar in order to allow this special
status to apply. What if it was a half a דינר? dinar?
Maybe there's an opinion that that would also be enough. אלא בפחות
מדינר קמיפלגי. ela be-pachos mi-dinar kamifligi. מר סבר דינר אין פחות מדינר
לא ומר סבר אפילו פחות מדינר. mar savar dinar in pachos mi-dinar
lo u-mar savar afilu pachos mi-dinar.
So maybe the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says they don't get it
because there wasn't a דינר's dinar worth left over and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon is saying you don't need a full דינר's dinar worth.
Okay? As long as there's even less than a דינר. dinar. והא
רבי שמעון דינר קאמר. ve-ha Rabbi Shimon dinar ka'amar.
So what type of crazy answer is that? So the גמרא Gemara
says והא רבי שמעון דינר קאמר. ve-ha Rabbi Shimon dinar ka'amar. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says there's a דינר. dinar. וכי תימא איפוך תנא
קמא דמתניתין נמי דינר קאמר. ve-chi teima ipoch Tanna Kamma de-masnisin nami
dinar ka'amar. And
if you say let's reverse it, maybe we're basically wound up saying
that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma requires less than a דינר dinar
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is being more strict and requires a
דינר. dinar. But it says the next משנה Mishna which remember we've
been quoting from the next משנה Mishna you're going to have רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon in this coming משנה mishna at the bottom of
the page and he's going to say an extra דינר. dinar. The
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma also says an extra דינר. dinar. So both
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon assume a
דינר dinar and that's assuming it's also the same positions in the
ברייתא we quoted. So we're still trying to figure out what are
they debating where the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says the kids of
the second one don't get out of Rachel's kids don't get it
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says they do get it. The most
easy thing to say is that they're debating exactly this fundamental principle
of אחת בחיי ואחת במותו. achas be-chayei ve-achas be-moso. But the גמרא's
Gemara trying to make it a more small technical more technical debate.
Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says אלא כי הנך תרי לישני קמאי ואיפוך. ela ki
hanech terei lishnei kamma'ei ve-ipoch. We'll go like the first two explanations
we said that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is basically saying
that the issue is about whether you need it to be from
land or even from chattel or whether the issue is about whether
you need to be encumbered or unencumbered. And we're going to reverse
it. Now what does it mean we're going to reverse it? So
there's the position of רש״י Rashi which is complicated which I'm not
going to get into. I'll just tell you the תוספות Tosafos read
but now I have to actually reread תוספות Tosafos to remind myself
how he reads it. Hold on.
Ah, so what he says is like this. We've been assuming that
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is more strict to Rachel's kids because
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma only mentions Leah's kids. It says Leah's
kids come and collect, right? It sounds like they're totally writing out
writing off Rachel's kids. And the problem okay that's what we've been
assuming. And the problem was that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon seems to
be writing in Rachel's kids, but he seems to also be being
more strict. He says if you've got a דינר dinar then you're
entitled. Sounds like he's making a new demand whereas actually what he's
doing is he's being more lenient. He's saying Rachel's kids can get
it. Okay? So what the גמרא's Gemara saying is let's assume that
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma actually the only reason the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma wrote off Rachel's kids was that the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma was talking about a case that there was no extra דינר.
dinar. So when the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said Leah's kids come
and get and he ignored Rachel's kids, that would be because there
was no extra דינר. dinar. That's the only reason. In principle Rachel's
kids should get according to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. But the
implicit point is once there's an extra דינר dinar then of course
Rachel's kids are going to get. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
is lenient as long as there's any extra דינר dinar the Rachel's
kids are going to get. Comes along רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is more strict. And this is רבי שמעון's
Rabbi Shimon language. No, only if there is a real extra דינר.
dinar. What does real extra דינר dinar mean? One of the two
things we said. Either real that it's of land and not chattel
and two it's unencumbered. Okay? So it's basically what we said before.
But the only reason we weren't able to say it before was
because we said the language sounds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
being strict and we were making it lenient. So now we're having
him being strict. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma ignored Rachel's kids because
there was no extra דינר, dinar, but once there's any extra דינר
dinar the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma will say Rachel's kids get it
and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, they're only going to get
it if it's a real extra דינר, dinar, if it's land and
unencumbered.
So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is not lenient.
Thank you very much.
Okay so I don't know.
Anyway we basically though if you got confused with all of that
again the basic point is we have the questions. When they're coming
from different positions, they're coming as special heirs, they're taking the שיעבודים,
shi'ubudim, in principle a ראוי כיוחזי ra'uy k'yuchzi title, it sounds like
we're moving to say yes, yes, yes, even though there's indications that
some would argue in principle, we keep on trying to insist everybody
would agree in principle Rachel's kids are entitled, but then the question
is what about the special other requirement, what about the other requirements
of being an extra דינא dina and so on, how exactly do
you determine what those criteria are? Do you satisfy it if you
use the money to pay off a creditor? Do you satisfy it
if it's chattel? Do you satisfy it if it's land but it's
encumbered? Those are the questions that are really at stake.
I want to know, I wanted to clarify how to read this,
when the גמרא Gemara says בני חורין bnei chorin or משעבדי, meshubadei,
are those phrases describing the human beings that they're not encumbered by
a loan?
No, no, the land, right.
So the land is can be described as בני חורין. bnei chorin.
Right, exactly.
That's what I wanted to know.
Is that for פרוטות? prutot? Is that what it is?
Yeah. So now the גמרא Gemara says, no, it's for זוז. zuz.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. ואיפכא. V'ipcha. אמר מר
זוטרא משמיה דרב פפא, Amar Mar Zutra mishmei d'Rav Pappa, we are
coming in for a landing. Okay, says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, says
מר זוטרא Mar Zutra in the name of רב פפא, Rav Pappa,
הלכתא, hilchata, the הלכה halacha is, אחת בחייו ואחת במותו יש להם
כתובת בני דכרין. achat b'chayav v'achat b'moto yesh lahem ketuvat bnei dichrin.
Thank you. There's a reason we kept on insisting and trying to
say that everybody said this, clearly the גמרא Gemara was coming to
the position that everybody, we don't want to acknowledge that anybody disagrees
with that. Everybody says that Rachel's kids are always entitled to their
special inheritance. Okay, which is makes sense, right? Again, going back to
the social reasons for this, societal reasons for this, if I'm going
to give my daughter a big whatever, a big dowry, what the
heck do I care whether, you know, whether the other wife's kids,
you know, whether the other wife died before or after the, you
know, the husband. I want my daughter's kids to get this dowry.
I'm not giving her a lot of money unless I know that
the dowry's going to her kids and not to somebody else's kids.
Okay, so it doesn't matter whether Leah's kids are going to feel
oh, it's not fair, we didn't get a special inheritance, tough luck.
Okay, Rachel's kids are always entitled to their special inheritance. Again, assuming
the principle of מותיר דינא. motir dina. One minute, one minute, let's
just read a little bit more. So it's Rachel's kids are always
entitled to it even if Leah's kids are coming from a different
perspective.
One minute,
did I skip a line? No.
הלכתא, hilchata, אחת בחייו ואחת במותו יש להם כתובת בני דכרין. achat
b'chayav v'achat b'moto yesh lahem ketuvat bnei dichrin. וכתובה נעשית מותיר לחברתה.
V'chetuvah na'asit motir l'chavertah. And also, if there has to be מותיר
motir leftover money for them to get it, but if there was
money that was used to pay off Leah's kids, that counts as
the leftover money. Okay, so because that's like Leah and Rachel's kids
inherited it all equally. Some of the money that they all equally
inherited were used up to pay off the creditors, which happened to
be Leah's kids. And therefore, that's allowed that is considered leftover money
so now Rachel's kids can come ahead and take their special portion.
Even if it was only ten thousand dollars?
No, no, you just needed something. If all that was left when
Reuben died was twenty thousand, so that Leah's kids were paid off
from the twenty thousand here, then ironically Rachel's kids get even less
because then there was nothing that they, you know, beyond the twenty
thousand that they all equally inherited. But if there was twenty thousand
and one dollar,
okay, and then Leah's kids were paid off, so now, you know,
so some of that cut into the twenty thousand, nevertheless, since one
of those dollars was used to pay off Leah's kids outside the
the chunk that Rachel's kids are going to get, then that was
a מותיר דינא motir dina and that entitled Rachel's kids to that
special chunk.
It wouldn't be ten thousand though because only because there's only twenty
thousand to begin with. Yeah. Yeah, so they're not really getting anything.
Well, yes they are because then they're not dividing the rest equally,
they're just taking all of the rest. Yes.
Does gender have to do with
inheritance here at all?
Absolutely. The daughters don't get anything. Now, now, wait, I shouldn't say
that because the same way there's this thing about, no, no, the
same way, I was being I was being a little flip because
the same biblically that's true.
But all of his children are girls.
Biblically we'll get no, then we'll get to that. And but biblically
there is the same way biblically the daughters don't get unless there's
no boys, but the same way there's this status of כתובת בני
דכרין ketuvat bnei dichrin which by the way means male sons to
give Rachel's kids a special a sort of a special status, there's
also a כתובה ketuvah. of a special כתובה ketuba of daughters, right,
which is basically that the daughters sort of became half heirs even
if there were sons and the rabbis gave them some special piece
of estate as well. But we haven't gone to that yet. Yes,
Jonathan.
Wasn't there a time in this section that we were sort of
elevating the בני דכרין bnei dichrin to status of בעלי חוב ba'alei
chov and giving them a preference?
Yes, good point. The גמרא Gemara made the point early on yesterday
and said from here it's clear that they're not, that they are,
right, that they're heirs, which has pluses and minuses, here it's got
somewhat of a minus because first Leah's kids get to take their
piece out.
And what about the top line?
All right, let's keep on reading. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, we didn't decide anything yet. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, okay, בשלמא, bishlama, so now the גמרא Gemara says why
did you have to tell me both of those principles, A that
Rachel's kids are entitled and B that paying off Leah's כתובה ketuba.
counts as the מותיר דינא. motir dina. בשלמא אי אשמעינן אחת בחיי
ואחת במותה bi-shlama i-ashmi-inan akhas be-khayyei ve-akhas be-mosa if you just told
me רחל's Rachel kids are entitled יש כתובת בנין דכרין yesh ketuvas
benin dikhrin ולא אשמעינן כתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה ve-lo ashmi-inan ketuvah na'asis
mosar le-khavertah
and you didn't say paying off לאה's Leah כתובה ketuba counted as
the extra money הוה אמינא hava amina
so then I wouldn't have known the second part. I would have
said איכא מותר דינר אין אי לא לא ika mosar dinar in
i lo lo only if there's leftover money after לאה's Leah kids
had been paid off not if the money paid off used to
pay off לאה's Leah kids doesn't count as the extra money. So
that's why you needed to tell me that. אלא ella but why
why not just tell me the second part of the statement לישמעינן
כתובה נעשית מותר לחברתה lishmi-inan ketuvah na'asis mosar le-khavertah just tell me
when when רחל's Rachel kids you know when the כתובה ketuba debt
is paid off that counts as extra money ואנא ידענא va-ana yadena
and I would have known משום דאחת בחיי ואחת במותה יש להם
כתובת בנין דכרין mishum de-akhas be-khayyei ve-akhas be-mosa yesh lahem ketuvas benin
dikhrin that the only reason you have to tell me that is
because you're telling me that רחל's Rachel kids are entitled. Right? You
don't say first of all רחל's Rachel kids are entitled. Second of
all if they're using the money to pay off לאה's Leah kids
that counts as the extra money. Okay. Now of course that's a
nice clear way to say it like why should you have to
tell me in as terse a way as possible to confuse me?
But okay. But the גמרא Gemara says why didn't you just tell
me you know what if if you use the money to pay
off לאה's Leah כתובה ketuba then רחל's Rachel kids you know that
counts as the extra money. I would have asked why are you
telling me that? It must mean that in principle רחל's Rachel kids
are entitled. So why did you have to tell me both stages?
So the גמרא Gemara, is going to tell me because of the
case of three wives. Okay. So
okay just when you thought we were actually coming to some clear
resolution here. So the
גמרא Gemara says אביי. Abaye.
Okay. So you know אי אשמעינן הכי i ashmi-inan hakh if you
had just start if the only thing you had said is paying
off לאה's Leah כתובה ketuba counts as the extra
money הוה אמינא hava amina I would have said that in the
case of רחל's Rachel kids and לאה's Leah kids like when some
are heirs and some are creditors רחל's Rachel kids don't get their
special their special role. So then why do you have to tell
me paying off a כתובה ketuba, counts as extra money? For the
following case. כגון שנשא שלוש נשים kegon she-nasa shalosh nashim if he's
married to three wives ומתו שתים בחייו u-mesu shtayim be-khayyo
רחל Rachel and לאה Leah died in his life and now רחל
Rachel and לאה's Leah kids are entitled to are both כתובת בנין
דכרין Ketubat Benin Dikhrin. and they're both coming on equal standing and
there there's no question that they both go ahead and take their
portion out. Right? The whole question was אחת בחיי ואחת במותה akhas
be-khayyei ve-akhas be-mosa different standing. Here they're equal standing. Their mothers both
died first. Their now father died. They're now coming to get their
special portions. Okay. But is there a מותר דינר mosar dinar or
not? Right? So the ones that got the bigger portion they want
there to be a מותר דינר. mosar dinar. Is there a מותר
דינר? mosar dinar? Well there was some some extra money left over
but you know what it's needed for? It's needed to pay the
כתובה ketuba of the third wife who's still alive.
Okay. So והכא דמייתה אחר מיתה יולדת נקבה היא ve-hakha de-miyisa akhar
misa yoledes nekeva hi and the third wife
she's only got girls. So then it's not like her heirs are
going to say oh it's unfair you guys got a special portion
and I didn't get a special portion. She's a girl so of
course she's not going to get a portion. So there's not that
question. So right you should be used to that.
So right exactly דלאו בת ירושה. de-lav bas yerusha. So in that
case they
will all be born female. Thank you.
So in that case there could be a reason to say that
paying off the כתובה ketuba. counts as מותר דינר mosar dinar and
still say that the principle of כתובת בנין דכרין Ketubat Benin Dikhrin,
only applies when everybody is on an equal when all the boys
are on an equal playing field. In the case of three wives
you would have needed that ruling. Okay. To say that since the
boys are on an equal playing field we have כתובת בנין דכרין.
Ketubat Benin Dikhrin. The extra דינר dinar exists because it was used
to pay off the third כתובה. ketuba. Okay.
אבל אחת בחיי ואחת במותה aval akhas be-khayyei ve-akhas be-mosa but I
might have still thought that if the boys are coming from different
levels one set is coming as heirs and the other set is
coming as creditors והדר אחר מיתה יולדת זכר היא ve-hadar akhar misa
yoledes zakhar hi and those that are coming right as creditors right
are male and therefore they they would have been heirs but now
they're coming as creditors אימא ליחוש לשינויא eima likhush le-shinuyei
I might be afraid that let's not let רחל's Rachel kids take
their special status as special heirs because לאה's Leah kids will say
wait we're heirs as well why do you guys get a special
status and we don't? קמשמע לן ka-mashma lan but we're not concerned
with that. So whew! So basically bottom line is that we say
אחת בחיי ואחת במותה akhas be-khayyei ve-akhas be-mosa רחל's Rachel kids are
still entitled to their special status as heirs as we said of
course that makes sense because that's going to encourage fathers you know
again in that sort of patriarchal society fathers to give dowries to
their daughters knowing it will stay with their family and it doesn't
matter that לאה Leah or her kids are coming you know from
a different perspective are coming as creditors and not as heirs they're
still entitled. But you still need and the idea you still need
that extra דינר dinar to allow all of this to take effect
that extra מותר mosar leftover money in the estate and that leftover
money though could even be money that is used to pay off
a creditor even money that's used off to pay לאה Leah or
her kids as well.
Twenty thousand and one.
Twenty thousand and one. Okay, now we're finally going to see in
this משנה mishna, everything we've been assuming, this rule of מותר דינר
mosar dinar and that question as we've already alluded to about what
that מותר דינר mosar dinar has to be. Yes.
What priority is the support of the surviving female children take?
So
the דק dak actually does take priority support to pretty much everything
else and we're going to see that as well. Okay, which is
basically הבנות יזונו והבנים יחזרו
על הפתחים. habanos yizonu v'habanim yachzeru al hapesachim. The daughters get fed
and the kids have to go begging, the sons have to go
begging.
Does he even say that the first children can actually come out
ten thousand ahead, for example, before they divide anything?
Yes, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, says like this. Phew!
מי שהיה
נשוי—so mi shehayah nasui now we get to the more basic case
of what we've been referring to. מי שהיה נשוי שתי נשים ומת.
mi shehayah nasui shtei nashim umes.
Wait, what'd I say? מתין? masin?
Okay, מי שהיה נשוי שתי נשים ומת.
mi shehayah nasui shtei
nashim umes.
All right, שתי נשים ומת. shtei nashim umes.
Somebody who was married to two wives and they both died before
he did. So now he saves paying out either of their כתובות.
ketubos. And both, but now he's going to die and both of
their kids are now finally going to want their mother's כתובה ketubah
paid out. They're going to come as heirs to their mother's כתובה.
ketubah ואחר כך מת, v'achar kach mes, and then he died. ויתומים
מבקשים כתובת אמן. v'yesomim mevakshim kesubas iman.
Now the heirs are, you know, רחל's Rachel kids and לאה's Leah
kids, each want to take their mother's כתובה ketubah, out of the
estate. ואין שם אלא שתי כתובות, v'ein sham ella shtei kesubos, and
there's only the exact amount in the estate to pay off רחל's
Rachel כתובה ketubah and לאה's Leah כתובה ketubah and nothing would be
left. Okay, so that's what we've been talking about, that nothing left
is the problem. So the הלכה halacha is חולקין בשוה. cholkin beshava.
So in that case, if there's going to be nothing left over,
everybody loses their special status and it's divided equally. So the only
people who want the special status are the ones that have the
bigger amount. Okay, by the way, it doesn't—I just want to just
point out—it doesn't even actually really have to be the bigger amount,
it just has to be proportionally bigger. Meaning if רחל Rachel has
one kid and לאה Leah has ten kids, right? Right. So they
could both have a כתובה ketubah of the exact equal amount, ten
thousand dollars. Okay, but רחל Rachel is going to want the special
rule to apply, רחל's Rachel kids, because then he goes away with
ten thousand dollars by himself, right? Whereas לאה's Leah kids, they would
have to divide it among ten, a thousand each. So the desire
to have the special status is not necessarily that your mother has
a bigger כתובה, Ksuba, but that it's your share is proportionally bigger.
Anyway, and they חולקין בשוה, cholkin beshava, meaning like, let's say if
רחל Rachel has one boy and לאה Leah has one boy, then
one boy would still get like two-thirds of it, right? Because he's
the בכור. bechor.
Yeah, yeah, let's—yes, but yes, you'd apply the laws of בכור bechor
too. Okay. Now, היה שם מותר דינר, hayah sham mosar dinar, if
there was a דינר dinar left over, finally now we're saying that
rule in this משנה, mishna after everybody would take out their special
inheritance. אלו נוטלין כתובת אמן ואלו נוטלין כתובת אמן. elu notlin kesubas
iman v'elu notlin kesubas iman. Then each side is entitled to take
out their mother's כתובה Ksuba. and then the what you divide the
estate with is that extra דינר. dinar. That goes to normal rules.
אם אמרו יתומים—now im amru yesomim here finally is of course what
everybody wants to know—the ones who want the special rule to apply,
but there's not going to be any leftover money in the estate.
They say, no problem, we'll make a donation to the estate, right?
אם אמרו יתומים אנחנו מעלים על נכסי אבינו יפה דינר. im amru
yesomim anachnu ma'alim al nichsei avinu yafeh dinar. We're going to go
ahead and we'll add money to the
estate כדי שיטלו כתובת אמן, kedei sheyitlu kesubas iman, in order that
they could go ahead and collect their mother's כתובה. Ksuba You know
what? אין שומעין להם. ein shomin lahem. You don listen to them.
Okay, what a surprise. So, אלא שמין
את הנכסים בבית דין. ella shamin es hanichasim beis din. Now, you
evaluate the money by the court. The court—assess, I should say, the
value, and that's what determines it or not. Now, by the way,
מעלים ma'alim might also not just mean we're going to add money
to the estate, but what they might actually say is, tell you
what we're going to do. We're going to be very generous. We're
going to take this piece of land which the court would estimate
it at eight thousand dollars, and we'll consider it to be worth
ten thousand dollars and we'll take that for our mother's כתובה. Ksuba
So even though they're sacrificing ten thousand dollars, in the end they're
benefiting because that allows them to have that special status because that's
going to leave over extra money in the estate. So the משנה
mishna is saying they don't get to determine how much it's worth
even if they're making it worth like more than it's really worth
and you know willing essentially to take a cut. That doesn't matter.
The court assesses what it's worth and the court is going to
determine whether there's extra money in the estate or not. One minute,
let's finish reading. היו שם נכסים בראוי, hayu sham nichasim barauy,
let's say there was money which was coming in, but it had
not yet arrived, okay? Which basically could mean that they're anticipating that
somebody is going to die and the estate will inherit other funds,
or it might even mean—עצים ופירות—or eitzim u'peiros it might even mean
that somebody owes money to the estate and they have not yet
collected those funds. So do you—accounts payable, accounts receivable—so do you consider
that part of the money of the estate to determine that there
is a מותר דינר mosar dinar in it or not? So אינן
כבמוחזק. einan kemuchzak. That is not like money under control of the
estate and that does not get counted.
Now, yeah, I mean, for—yeah, but it depends on the case. רבי
שמעון אומר—now Rabbi Shimon omer finally we get the רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. Earlier, אפילו יש שם נכסים שאין להם אחריות אינם כלום, Afilu
yesh sham nechasim she-ein lahem achrayut einam klum,
even if there is money leftover money but it is not, it
is chattel, it is not land, that doesn't count either.
There has to be land that goes beyond the value of the
two כתובות ktubot worth a דינר. dinar. Wait, Jonathan had his hand
up first. Go ahead, Jonathan.
Do we know that there could be a discussion of בני דכרין
Bnei Dikhrin or at least these two different sets of orphans, one
with a larger claim than the other?
No, nobody has any larger claim. The only reason you'd have a
larger claim, the only person who has a larger claim if it's
ירושין yerushin is the בכור. bechor. Otherwise no set has a larger
claim, right?
I meant a larger כתובה Ksuba, amount.
No, no, no, so if the larger כתובה Ksuba amount, that's because
it's כתובת בנין דכרין. Ketubat Benin Dikhrin The only reason you have
a larger claim, because you have a larger כתובה, Ksuba is כתובת
בנין דכרין. Ksubas Benin Dichrin If it wasn't כתובת בנין דכרין, Ksubas
Benin Dichrin. who cares how much how big your mother's כתובה was?
It never got paid out. The mother died before the father. The
only reason you're entitled to take out that amount is because of
כתובת בנין דכרין. Benin Dikhrin? That says that even though the mother
died and she never took out the כתובה amount, now that my
father has died, that allows me to get this bigger portion of
the estate.
So it is referring to בנין דכרין?
Benin Dichrin Exactly, yes.
Chattel could be worth a fortune though.
So that's why רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position is that, you know,
it represents the sort of symbolic significance of of the estate, right?
I mean, you know, if you think you read the end of
במדבר Bamidbar or whatever, the whole big thing is like they're dividing
up the land and בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzelofchad, which is like is
all about a portion in the land, right? So it's that sort
of represents the ancestral estate, so it's that symbolic significance. Yes.
You have built-in הלכה Halacha that the בית דין Beit Din can't
be egregious in over-assessing.
But it puts power in the hand of the
בית דין Beit Din to
to
apply the rabbinic instruments to ensure that the father would know that
the daughter's inheritance is going to...
It's an interesting point, like how much is בית דין Beit Din
going to be just guided because there's always going to be a
certain amount of discretion, right? I mean, how do you estimate the
cost of this? It's the Bluebook value of the car, is it
this, is it that or whatever? How much is בית דין Beit
Din going to sort of try to do it in order to
ensure that כתובת בנין דכרין kicks in...
To maintain the biblical foundation but to also ensure the rabbinic instrument.
Yeah, it's an interesting point. Yes.
I was going to talk about that because this משנה mishna. is
more גמרא-like Gemara in terms of have we crossed the line because
there's no fixed price of the real estate. It's always subject to
negotiation. Right. So there's no such thing as the the reality. This
is more of a the גמרא Gemara
thing and the גמרא, Gemara you
know, comes up with some ingenious way to resolve it all that
isn't always so far.
Right, but you have to do your best. I mean, you know,
when you get a property assessor to come and determine it for
property taxes or whatever, right? It's not in the end the amount
of money that you're going to get if you were to ever
sell it, but you have to be able to put some theoretical
price tag on it. Yeah.
Two questions. One, the last thing about not dealing with the movable
property, was that is this affected by the later תקנה Takana of
the גאונים Geonim where you could inherit contracts?
Assuming we were to פסקן pasken like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, you're
saying would it be affected what since the time of the גאונים
Geonim when we had they moved to a completely commercial society so
the status of קרקע, karka, you know, chattel had been given equal
weight to קרקע. karka. That could be. That would be relevant if
we פסקן pasken רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, which it looks like we
actually do based on the לשון Leshon here, so I'd have to
see how that developed. Yeah.
And the second is accounts payable similarly for accounts receivable, they now
are known to have cash value and might they actually be considered
as that?
Aha.
Yeah, I don't know. We'll take a look. We're not going to
get today. I mean, we have seven minutes anyway, but we're not
even on today's דף up to the issue about ראוי raui and
מוחזק, muchzak, so we'll talk about that tomorrow.
Yeah, I was going to ask, is this applies today? Do we
have a different framework because our economy is today?
Yes, so that's similar to what Charlie asked. So, oh, you're saying
in terms of the issue about accounts payable, accounts receivable, maybe that
also would be reassessed based on how we look at it nowadays.
It's an interesting question. I don't know. All right, let's take a
look. Let's see if we can get to turning the page. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, לזו אלף ולזו חמש מאות. Le-zo elef u-le-zo chamesh
meot.
So one set of kids their mother's כתובה is a thousand, the
other set is 500. So the ones that are a thousand want
this special rule to apply. אם יש שם מותר דינר אלו נוטלין
כתובת אמן ואלו נוטלין כתובת אמן ואם לאו יחלקו בשווה. Im yesh
sham motar dinar, elu notlin ktubat iman ve-elu notlin ktubat iman, ve-im
lav yachloku be-shaveh.
All right, so that doesn't add too much to the משנה. Mishnah
Nevertheless, if there's 1501, then they then they each one gets their
special status; if not, they divide it equally. Now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: פשיטא, Pshita, it's obvious to me, says the גמרא,
Gemara מרובין ונתמעטו. merubin ve-nismatu.
There was, let's take let's use the immediate previous case that we
just quoted. There was 1501 dollars in the estate when the guy
died, and now stuff has depreciated or the market has changed and
now it's only worth 1400. Okay. So כבר זכו בהן יורשין. kevar
zachu bahen yorshin.
So the יורשין yorshin got their special status, right? Because you look
at the property at the time that the guy died and the
value of the estate at that time.
Even if it hasn't been divided? Is that what you're saying?
Even if it hasn't been divided. Now the question might be even
if it might even be even what if it's even before בית
דין Beit Din assessed? Let's say בית דין Beis Din assessed a
month after the guy died but they looked at... Back and they
were upset but at the time he died it actually was worth
1501. That might be enough. Okay, so that's an interesting question, when
do you determine its value for this. So he says if it
sounds like okay, it goes by what it originally was. We're not,
we have not made clear when the assessment took place.
How about
however מועטין ונתרבו? Muatin venisrabu? Let's say when the guy died it
was 1490
and now then it's maybe when בית דין Beit Din assessed it
or they're coming to collect it or whatever, maybe now it's 1501,
should that maybe say look, as long as in any situation you
can allow these כתובת בנין דכרין to kick in, you know, you'll
go by it. Whether it goes by the state originally or whether
it goes by the state now, if you always just go by
the way it was when the guy died. So let's take a
look. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come and hear. דנכסי דבי בר צרצור,
Denichsei d'Bei Bar Tsartsur, the property of the house of
צרצור, Tsartsur, the guy's name or whatever, מועטין ונתרבו הוו Muatin venisrabu
havu was exactly this case: when he died there was not enough
to pay out the כתובות Ksubos and then it became the property,
the value went up. ואתו לקמיה דרב אמי V'asu lekamei d'Rav Ami
and the heirs came to רב אמי. Rav Ami. אמר להו Amar
lehu he said to them, זילו
פייסוהו. Zilu paysuhu. Go and, the way רש"י Rashi explains it is,
he said to the ones that were coming with the smaller כתובה,
go, you know, make some deal with the ones with the big
כתובה. Okay, which basically means to say like, it sounds like he's
basically saying that in principle the ones with the bigger כתובה will
be entitled to take their portion out now that it's worth more.
And if you don't want that to happen, you'd better try to
make some deal with them. Okay,
so that's a little vague what exactly he was ruling, but he
was trying to get them to come to some פשרה Pshara or
something. Okay. לא אשגחו, Lo ashgechu, they ignored them. אמר להו Amar
lehu he said to them, אי לא מפיסיתו להו Ei lo mefaisitu
lehu if you don't try to appease them, מחינא לכו בסילוא דלא
מבע דמא. Machina lachon besilu d'lo mava dma.
I will hit you with a like with a board with a
thorn that does not draw blood. What thorn doesn't draw blood? The
thorn of rabbinic excommunication. So it'll be very painful but it will
not be physical pain. Okay, so
anyway he was trying to compel them to come to some type
of a deal, which might mean that he did not know how
to rule, so he was trying to get them to come to
some פשרה Pshara or something. Okay. שדרינהו, Shadrinhu, that was not getting
anywhere.
Right, so you
know using
strong arm tactics didn't get him anywhere. So he sent them לקמיה
דרב נחמן Lekamei d'Rav Nachman to רב נחמן Rav Nachman to resolve
this. אמר להם Amar lahem רב נחמן Rav Nachman said to them,
כשם שמרובין ונתמעטו Keshem shemerubin venismatu the same way when there are
a lot and then they go down in value, זכו בהן יורשין,
Zachu vahen yorshin, the heirs of the bigger, you know, of the
bigger portion get it, כך מועטין ונתרבו Kach muatin venisrabu
similarly when it's a little and it's now bigger, זכו בהן יורשין
Zachu vahen yorshin the heirs get it. Now of course the big
question is which heirs? Right? So רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos debate
what the conclusion was. רש"י Rashi says it means that the heirs
of the smaller amount wind up benefiting, that actually
you always go by what it was at the time of death.
And תוספות Tosafos says no, the language is exactly the same, זכו
בהן יורשין. Zachu vahen yorshin.
So if when it was a big and it went down, the
heirs of the bigger כתובה got their bigger כתובה, so when it
was a little and went up, the heirs of the bigger כתובה
get their bigger כתובה and you always like tip in favor of
applying the rules of כתובת בנין דכרין. Okay, so this is the
question: do you always go by the value
of the estate when the guy died, or do you always go
by either what it was worth then or what it's worth now,
if either one of those will allow us to apply the rule
of the special status of heirs? So that's what תוספות Tosafos says.
תוספות Tosafos says you always try to apply the special status of
בנין דכרין and רש"י Rashi says you always go by the time
the guy died. All right, let's try to read one more case.
ההוא גברא דהוה מסקי ביה אלפא זוזי, Hahu gavra d'hava masekei bei
alfa zuzei, a certain person, he owed a thousand dollars. הוו ליה
תרי אפדני Havu lei terei apadnei and
he had two houses, yeah, some type of a mansion, right. Okay,
two houses. זבינהו חד בחמש מאה וחד בחמש מאה. Zavinhu chad bechamesh
mea vechad bechamesh mea. He went and he sold each one at
five hundred. So I owe somebody a thousand dollars, I sold my
two houses to Michael for five hundred bucks each. Now I've got
the cash and I can, you know, pay off my בעל חוב,
Ba'al chov, but who knows, maybe I went ahead and I wasted
that on a trip to Las Vegas. So now my בעל חוב
Ba'al chov still needs his thousand bucks and he's going to go
to Michael, who's got two houses each one worth five hundred dollars.
So what did he do? אתא בעל חוב טרפא לחדא מינייהו. Asa
ba'al chov taraf lachada mineihu. He came to Michael and he took
the first house for five hundred dollars, and Michael saw he was
about to now take the second house. Now Michael really liked these
houses, he didn't want the guy to take the houses. So what
is Michael going to do? So Michael went ahead and says the
following: הדר קא טרף לאידך, Hadar ka taraf l'idach, he's about to
take the second house. שקל אלפא זוזי וקאזיל לגביה, Shakal alfa zuzei
vekazil legabei, so Michael took a thousand dollars and went to him,
the creditor. אמר ליה Amar lei he said to him, look, אי
שוו לך אלפא זוזי לחיי. Ei shavu lach alfa zuzei lechai.
I'm going to tell you something. buddy, the first house you took
I think in my eyes it's worth a thousand dollars. I think
your debt is paid up. If you want to consider it that
that's the full thousand dollars and the debt is paid up, fine,
then leave me alone and don't take the second house. Now, he
says the guy says I don't think it's worth a thousand dollars,
I don't think it's worth 500. Fine. So he says ואי לא
שקול אלפי זוזי ואיסתלק ve'ei lo shekul alfei zuzei ve'istalek fine, you
don't think it's worth a thousand dollars? So
here, take a thousand dollars and give me back the house. Okay,
which basically means that Michael wants to keep at least one of
the houses, if not both of them. Okay, so basically what he's
going to do is he's going to say to the guy I
will assess the value of that first house at a thousand dollars.
If you don't like that assessment, okay,
then I will pay you the thousand dollars but you're not going
to be entitled to take both houses. So are you sort of
like entitled to negotiate as it were with the person and to
claim here's what I'm assessing the value to be? You don't like
that fine I'll give you a thousand dollars elsewhere but don't take
the two houses. Okay?
So the גמרא says what could a בית דין Beit Din have
something?
Well, yeah, so that's גמרא'ס Gemara's question and the גמרא'ס Gemara's going
to say that seems to be similar to the משנה Mishnah: with
the heirs are saying we'll consider this to be worth X amount
that will then entitle it to be that there'll be extra money
left in the estate. So are you allowed to do that if
at a certain level it's to your own detriment
because in principle you're doing it because it benefits you in terms
of your negotiation. Generally?
Yeah, in general if
if the debtor comes to the guy who bought the house on
the money yeah he doesn't have the right to buy him out?
So that's what תוספות Tosafot discusses. תוספות Tosafot wants to know does
this reflect a general principle that the guy can always say take
cash don't take the thing you've got a lien on. So it
sounds like it might. Of course if it did then you wouldn't
have to say that he was giving a special value to it.
So תוספות Tosafot tries to work that out. Let's just read one
line in the גמרא and we'll end with that for today. The
גמרא says like this: סבר רמי בר חמא למימר היינו מתניתין, Savar
Rami bar Chama lemeimar hainu matnitin, this is our משנה: אם אמרו
יתומים הרינו מעלים על נכסי אבינו יפה דינר, im amru yetomim harenu
ma'alim al nichsei avinu yafeh dinar, that the heirs say we're going
to evaluate it to be worth more and we don't like that
we say בית דין has to evaluate it, you're not entitled to
assess what it's worth. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא
Rava said מי דמי? mi dami? Is that the same? התם איכא
פסידא, Hatam ika pseida, there by one set of heirs giving it
a higher value the other set of heirs lose out
because then it doesn't get divided equally ליתומי. le'yatmi. הכא מאי פסידא?
Hacha mai pseida?
Since the creditor isn't losing out אלפא יהיב ואלפא שקיל. alfa yahiv
ve'alfa shakil. So maybe he wanted those nice houses but at the
end of the day he's getting his full thousand dollars. So maybe
Michael is in a position to say buddy, if you want to
keep that I'm saying it's worth a thousand dollars. You don't like
that fine, take the cash, but you're not entitled to take both
houses. So the גמרא doesn't exactly know and just end and it
says like this: וטירפא דכמה כתבינן. v'tirpa d'kama katvinan. So the
גמרא pretty much assumes that maybe actually Michael is entitled to say
that. So the guy went ahead and he's said fine I really
want the house I don't want your thousand dollars I'll just take
one house. I would have liked to take two but given that
you're saying what you're saying I'll just take one. Now Michael's going
to come back to me and say hey Dov you owe me
money because one of the houses I bought was just taken by
the creditor. How much money can Michael get from me? By giving
the guy one house he's now freed me of my full thousand
dollar loan. Okay but he only lost out five hundred dollars of
his purchase price. How much reimbursement is he entitled to get from
me? So we'll just read this one line. So it says like
this: כמה כתבינן. kama katvinan. רבינא אמר באלפא, Ravina amar be'alfa, he's
entitled to get a thousand dollars because he basically got me out
of a thousand dollar loan and that's essentially how much it was
worth. He says hey it seems that it was worth a thousand
dollars, the creditor took it for that, give me back a thousand
dollars. ואידך אמר, ve'idach amar, and the other one says רב אשי
אמר בחמש מאה. Rav Ashi amar b'chamesh me'ah. No, it was only
five hundred. You made a very brilliant deal there but bottom line
is you only lost a field worth five hundred dollars. והלכתא בחמש
מאה. ve'hilchta b'chamesh me'ah. So I really only have to give him
back five hundred dollars. So everybody wins. I only paid up five
hundred dollars for a thousand dollar loan, Michael got to keep one
of his houses, the creditor got his thousand dollars, שלום על ישראל.
Shalom al Yisrael. Okay. That's a great place to break.
Yeah, story for today.